那么，
在这个演示中，
我将介绍比特币挖矿是如何工作的。
我将从什么是挖矿开始，
然后解释它是什么以及为什么存在。
然后，
我将介绍它是如何工作的。
但在我解释它是如何工作的之前，
我需要解释什么是哈希函数，
因为这是比特币工作的一个重要部分。
我会先介绍它的基本工作原理，
然后我将再次介绍它，
我将以更专业的方式来解释。
所以，
如果你是一个程序员，
你会发现这更有趣。
我将开始做一些例子，
并尝试向你展示如何在非常少的代码中实际挖掘一个实时块。
那么，什么是挖矿?
假设这是比特币网络，
这些都是连接在一起运行比特币程序的计算机，
共享同一个文件，
即区块链。
比特币的工作方式是，
如果你想向某人发送比特币，
或者将比特币的所有权转让给别人，
你需要创建一个交易，
这只是一行数据，
然后你将其插入到网络上的一个节点中。
然后，
如果我们没有挖矿，
这个计算机将直接将其写入区块链，
然后它们会将这个交易传递给它们连接的节点，
将其写入自己的文件，
如此反复，
直到这个交易在整个网络中传播，
并写入他们的共享文件。
是拥有共享文件或共享交易的一种简单方法
你知道的，
当每个人都更新了他们的文件副本，
比特币的所有权就从一个人转移到了另一个人，
这是一个简单的交易。
但是，如果你这样做，
会有一个问题需要解决。
让我们把这个人涂成绿色……
你要做的就是创建一个交易，
将比特币发送给这个人
并将其插入网络的这一侧的一个节点。
但是，由于这是一个连接的计算机网络，
你要创建第二个交易，
将同样的比特币发送给另一个人。
所以，
你刚刚在网络中插入了两个试图花费同一比特币的交易，
你可以这样做，
因为这是一个网络。
接下来会发生的是，
这两个交易将开始在网络中传播。
你可以看到，
这边的计算机已经收到了这个红色的交易和第二个交易，
但是这边的计算机已经收到了绿色的交易。
当这台计算机试图将绿色的交易传递给这台计算机时，
这台计算机已经收到了花费这个比特币的红色交易，
所以它们会拒绝它，
这是对的。
但是，
你仍然有一个问题，
那就是网络中存在这两个冲突的交易，
或者你从整个网络或者这个文件的角度来看，
这个比特币现在属于谁。
所以，如果你以这种方式运行比特币，
并直接将交易写入文件，
你可能会创建这个双重支付问题。
但是，比特币基本上解决了这个问题，
将不将冲突的交易写入区块链或这个共享文件，
这就是挖矿的含义。
比特币解决这个双重支付问题的方式，
这就是比特币有趣的地方，
因为我们以前有过这种技术，
*麦克风有问题，稍等*
比特币解决了将两个冲突的交易写入共享文件的问题。
这就是比特币的有趣之处，
也是我认为比特币的“发明”成功之处
比特币解决这个问题的方式是，
它给运行比特币程序的每台计算机一些临时内存，
称为内存池。
你不能阻止这种双重支付攻击，
接下来会发生的是，
这个人会在这台计算机中插入一个交易，这个绿色的交易，
这个绿色的交易，
然后他们可以去这里做同样的攻击
再次将这个第二个红色交易插入这台计算机。
但显然，
这两个交易并没有直接写入文件，
它们首先被存储在临时内存中。
然后，
同样的事情再次发生，
两个交易在网络中传播，
这个节点会拒绝绿色交易，
因为他们已经接收到了红色交易。
所以我们看到，
两个交易都在网络中，
但它们还没有写入文件，
所以文件仍然是安全的。
然后会发生的事情是，
所有的这些计算机都会努力尝试从他们的内存池中获取交易，
并将其添加到文件中。
所以他们基本上都在竞争，
要成为第一个将内存池中的交易添加到文件中的节点。
假设这个节点是第一个能够做到的，
他们将他们的内存池中的交易添加到文件中，
就像这样……
当他们这样做的时候，
他们会将更新后的文件副本传递给他们连接的所有其他节点，
然后他们会更新他们的副本。
这个节点，
因为他们的内存池中有这个冲突的绿色交易，
但他们刚刚接收到这个红色交易，
消费了同样的比特币，
他们会将这个绿色交易从他们的内存池中剔除。
这个内存池就像一个等待区域或者一个清算所，
他们接收到了这个红色交易在更新的文件中，
然后他们会剔除这个冲突的交易。
然后这个节点会将更新的副本传递给这些节点，
他们也会做同样的事情，
他们会从他们的内存池中剔除任何冲突的交易。
这就是你如何解决网络中有两个冲突交易的问题的方法，
你只需要有一个等待区域，
所有的节点都在竞争，
试图将他们的交易添加到文件中，
这个过程就叫做挖矿，
这个人获得了比特币。
所以这个过程，
每个节点都在竞争，
试图从他们的内存池中获取交易，
然后添加到文件中，
这就叫做挖矿，
这就是我现在要解释的。
那么，
到目前为止有问题吗?
但是这里需要注意的一点是，
网络中的每个节点并不一定都在挖矿。
是的，
我做了一个非常简单的图表来尝试解释这个问题。
有些节点可能并不是在挖矿，
你可以只运行一个节点来传递区块和交易信息。
但在这个简化的图表中，
每个节点都在尝试挖矿。
我们也可以设想一个不挖矿的节点，
如果它收到一个包含交易信息的区块
而内存池中有一个与之冲突的交易，
它会将其移除。
是的
所有的区块和交易信息传递，
节点都会做这个工作，
但是矿工只会做这最后一部分，
试图从内存池中添加交易信息。
这就是矿工的工作，
你可以成为一个节点，而不必挖矿。
而不必挖矿。
我的介绍还可以吗？
接下来我要解释的是哈希函数，
然后我会讲解比特币挖矿是如何工作的。
好的，
哈希函数其实就是一个小型的计算机程序，
它的工作方式是你可以将一些数据输入到哈希函数中，
哈希函数会将其打乱并产生一个随机的数据字符串作为结果。
哈希函数的一个有用的特性是，
你可以将相同的数据输入到它中，
它总是会输出相同的结果，
也就是以相同的方式打乱数据以产生这个随机的数据字符串。
这个数据字符串的大小总是相同的，
为32字节或64个字符，
因为每个字节有两个字符。
如果你对输入到哈希函数中的数据做一个微小的调整，
比如从a1变为a2，
结果会完全不同。
我们只做了一个微小的调整，
但哈希函数的结果却大不相同。
再次输入a3，
微小的调整，
结果还是完全不同。
哈希函数的一个重要特性是，
如果你事先不知道结果，
就无法预测a2会输出什么。
结论：
如果你事先不知道这个结果，
就无法预测结果到是什么，
这是很有用的，
我们稍后会看到。
最后，
尽管这看起来像一个随机的数据字符串，
它包含了字母f、e、a，
基本上是a、b、c、d、e和f，
但它们实际上可以转换成数字。
这是因为我们习惯于使用十进制格式的数字，
它使用0到9的数字，
但你也有一种叫做十六进制的数字格式，
它使用相同的数字，
但也包括a、b、c、d、e和f，
当你转换它们时，
它们就像这样。
所以，
这被称为十进制，
因为它使用10，
deci在拉丁语中意思是10。
然后十六进制，
hexa就像六边形一样有六个边，
deci 10，6 10 16。
所以，
基本上这是我们人类使用的，
但计算机非常乐意以十六进制格式读取数字。
基本上来说，
你把数据放入哈希函数，
它会输出一个随机数作为结果。
如果你看到一个像这样的十六进制格式字符串，
记住这只是一个随机数。
这个概念很容易理解了吧？
好的，
那就是哈希函数，
它只是一个输出随机数据的小工具。
如果我快速给你展示一下，
我不知道你们是否能看到，
是否能读懂
但如果你能看到，
哈希函数在很多编程语言中都有。
例如，在PHP中，
有一个叫做hash()的函数，
然后你可以告诉它你想使用哪种哈希函数，
比如sha256，
这是比特币中使用的一种，
它代表的是简单哈希算法256位，
这是它输出结果的大小，
然后你可以把你想要哈希的内容放进去。
好了。
这就是结果，
你可以在任何编程语言中使用哈希函数
我刚刚展示了如何在PHP中使用它
这是在Ruby中，
只是为了完整
它包含在'digest'库中，
所以你可以输入:' puts digest::SHA56
然后我们需要一个十六进制摘要…
“摘要”只是从哈希函数中得到的结果的另一个术语
所以我把“a1”代入这里，
这里我们得到了同样的东西，
所以
哈希函数在很多编程语言中都是可用的
现在我将介绍挖矿的基本原理，
我将给出一个简单的例子
说明如何从内存池获取交易并将其添加到区块链中。
所以，
挖矿的基本原理是，
所有的交易都在内存池中。
*调整麦克风*
我们继续来看到这个计算机，
这个节点是一个矿工，
我们来看看它的内部，
看看它是如何从内存池中挖取交易到其文件的。
*他调整麦克风*
我们继续，查看比特币矿工的内部情况。
这是内存池，
里面有红色的是交易。
交易在内存池中，
但内存池中可以有多个交易。
假设这个内存池已经有了很多交易。
挖矿者会创建一个叫做候选块的容器，
这只是一个交易的容器。
他们会用内存池中的交易填充这个候选块，
就像这样，
然后他们会试图将这个交易块添加到区块链上。
那么他们如何将这个他们构建的候选块添加到区块链上呢？
首先，
他们会构建一个被称为区块头的东西，
这只是块内所有数据的摘要，
所有区块内的交易，
在那个区块头中，
你有一个被称为版本的东西，
这就像是数据结构的版本号，
假设那是1。
还会有一些被称为
前一个区块或前一个区块哈希的信息。
这个工作方式是，
假设这是区块链，
他们正在构建的这个候选块必须建立在这些区块之一的顶部。
所以挖矿者会做的是，
他们会包含他们想要建立在其顶部的区块的哈希或区块哈希，
这就像是一个区块的id号。
所以在这里，
这是这个区块的区块哈希。
所以这只是说他们想要建立在哪个区块的顶部，
因为每个挖矿者基本上都想要建立在区块链的顶部。
我来讲解“默克尔根”是什么
基本上如果你把所有的交易ID一起哈希，
反复的哈希，
你最后会得到一个单独的哈希，
这就叫做梅克尔根。
就像这样，
这基本上就像一个指纹，
一个数字指纹，
总结了区块中的所有交易。
所以，
你知道这个区块头，
它创建了一个独特的指纹，
用于所有的区块数据，
但使用的数据比所有的交易数据组合起来要少得多。
或许你能谈一谈默克尔根
因为我没有听说过太多关于它的事情。
你是在哈希每一笔交易，
然后哈希那些结果吗？
是的，我会在接下来的技术部分中介绍这个，
但只要现在你需要知道：
涵盖所有区块交易的总结就可以了。
默克尔根是非常有意义的。
我会在一会儿介绍梅克尔是如何工作的，
以及为什么使用梅克尔，
这是一个好问题。
这是区块头，
我没有涵盖所有的区块头数据，
那么这就是是最重要的东西。
现在我们有了一个区块头，
下一步就是将这个区块头数据放入哈希函数，
也就是SHA-256哈希函数中，
然后这将产生一个随机数作为结果，
这就是所谓的区块哈希。
到目前为止你有任何问题吗？
好的，
这很好，我们继续，
但是为什么矿工要这么做呢？
或者说，这如何帮助将区块挖掘到区块链上呢？
如果这个区块哈希，
也就是将区块头放入哈希函数产生的结果，
生成一个低于“Target”值的块哈希值
就像这样，
假设这是当前的目标值，
这是每个比特币节点内部的一个数字，
他们都有一个共享的目标值，
这个目标值与其他节点同步计算。
他们能让他们的区块哈希值低于这个目标值，
那么这个区块就会被添加到区块链上，
这个问题基本上解决了。
所以，
到目前为止，
这是第一次尝试，
你们可以看到，
这个数字显然比目标值大，
所以它不低于目标，
所以，
这第一次尝试添加这个区块到区块链上失败了。
然后，矿工并不放弃。
在区块头中，
有一个额外的字段叫做nonce，
它代表一次性使用的数字。
这是一个开放的字段，
矿工可以自由地放入他们自己的数字或数据。
所以，
如果区块头的第一次尝试失败，
他们可以改变nonce值或改变nonce中的数据。
例如，
第一次尝试可能他们在那里放了数字零，
如果那失败了，
他们会改变nonce，
然后再次将区块头通过哈希函数。
因为我们只做了一点小的调整
就像我之前给你们展示的哈希函数，
小的调整可以产生完全不同的结果。
所以，矿工基本上会构造一个区块头，
并不断改变这个nonce值，
希望结果会产生一个低于目标值的区块哈希。
所以，矿工实际上是创建一个区块头，
然后在末尾添加一个nonce，
如果不成功，
他们会不断增加尝试，
这完全是随机的，
…这只是纯粹的随机性和纯粹的运气…
他们可能能够猜到一个有效的随机数，
产生一个低于目标的区块哈希。
所以，
这个特定的非常高的随机数产生了一个成功的区块哈希结果。
然后，
这个节点会将该区块添加到他们的区块链中，
并将这个已解决的候选区块传递给他们连接的所有节点。
他们会检查并验证区块头确实产生了一个低于目标的区块哈希，
然后将其添加到文件中，
剔除包含在该区块中的任何冲突交易，
然后像这样传递区块。
他们也会做同样的事情。
这就是挖矿在基本层面上的工作方式。
我有个问题，
你说的目标值，
每个节点都有自己的目标值，
对吗？我想过这个问题，
但是有可能我挖到的区块低于我的目标值，
然后我把它给我的邻居节点，
可能目标值已经改变了，
或者出于某种原因，
其他节点的目标值不同。
是的，
我明白你的问题。
我想我已经解释过目标了，
可能我没有解释得很好，
我再解释一下。
目标的存在是为了确保每10分钟会有一个新的区块被挖出。
但是，
如果有更多的计算机以更快的速度进行哈希运算，
那么一个区块可能会在10分钟内被挖出。
因此，
这个目标值会上下浮动，
以确保每10分钟挖出一个新的区块。
当你首次运行比特币并挖出第一个区块时，
目标值是硬编码在这个值中的。
然后，每过2016个区块，
或者大约每两周，
每个节点都会查看挖出最后2016个区块所需的时间。
预期的时间显然是20160分钟，
但如果实际挖出这些区块的时间少于这个时间，
那么，目标会进行调整。
目标会按照这个比例进行调整。
所以，
这个比例是因为所有的区块都被挖掘得更快，
所以它是0.9。
所以你可以看到，
这个目标会向下调整。
所以每个节点在接收到一个新的区块后，
每2016个区块，
他们都会做这个精确的计算。
然后每个节点都从这个值开始，
但是如果每个人都在同一个区块，
那么每个人都会计算出同样的目标。
所以基本上每个人都有同样的目标，
他们都自己计算，
但是因为他们都接收到同样的区块，
他们都会计算出同样的目标值。
所以不是每个人都有不同的目标值，
个人都有同样的计算目标。
所以再次强调，
这每2016个区块就会发生一次，
同样的事情会发生，
他们花了多长时间，
比例是多少，挖掘得更快，
就再次向下调整，
就像这样。
那么，
这就是Target 是如何工作的。
到目前为止，
我已经把这个区块链称为一个共享文件，
这个共享文件是一个区块链。
基本上，这个共享文件充满了交易，
因为交易是以区块的形式添加的，
这个文件被称为区块链，
因为每个区块都在彼此之上建立。
所以对于比特币来说，
它是一个共享文件，
这个共享文件被称为区块链。
所以如果我更新这个图，
你可以把这个共享文件想象成就是一堆堆叠在一起的区块。
最后，
为什么有人会挖矿呢？
对于矿工来说，
他们为什么要在他们的电脑上使用所有这些哈希算力
来尝试从内存池中挖掘交易到区块链呢？
每次矿工成功挖掘一个区块，
们都会得到一个叫做区块奖励的东西。
它开始时是50，
但大约每四年就会减半。
所以这就是挖掘一个区块的激励。
当矿工构建候选区块时，
他们会得到这个区块奖励。
第一笔交易是他们自己的。
矿工会把他们自己的交易放在最顶部，
这叫做coinbase交易。
这是一种特殊的交易，
因为它允许他们向自己发送一定数量的比特币，
这些比特币之前并不存在。
所以，
如果这个区块被挖掘到区块链上，
他们将能够通过这个coinbase交易接收新的比特币。
多亏了这个coinbase交易，
他们在这里放置他们的比特币地址，
以便他们可以接收区块奖励。
总结一下挖矿的基本步骤，
矿工会从内存池中获取交易，
然后他们会在顶部放置他们的coinbase交易，
以便如果他们成功挖掘这个区块到区块链上，
可以接收区块奖励。
然后他们会创建一个区块头，
对其进行哈希。
希望哈希值低于目标值，
如果不是，
他们会不断调整nonce，
直到他们领先于别人找到一个nonce，
这个nonce产生的区块哈希值低于目标值。
然后他们会将区块添加到区块链上。
像这样。你理解了吗?
你理解了吗?
okay
我现在将向你展示一个小型的挖矿模拟器。
这就是比特币矿机在内部可能看起来的样子。
他们会进入他们的内存池，
从内存池中获取交易。
这个挖矿模拟器正在挖掘一个已经被挖掘过的区块，
这是很久以前的事情，
内存池中只有13个交易。
现在显然更多了。
然后它们会做什么呢，
它们会构建区块头，
我还没有介绍区块头的最后两部分，
不过别担心，
我马上就会介绍。
但这些数据是指前一个区块...
有默克尔根，版本号。
然后他们会做的是，
把所有这些数据压缩成一行数据。
我在这里留了一些空间用于nonce，
这是区块头数据，
这是目标值。
然后矿工会做的是，
他们会取这个区块头，
并在其中放入一个nonce，
不断增加它，
正如你现在看到的。
这是一个非常慢的矿工，
你可以看到这些是左边的随机数值，
这些是区块头正在产生的不同的哈希值。
好的，
所以当你在顶部创建那个字符串...？
那并没有包括交易，
只包括了区块头？
是的
哦，好的。
交易我想是包含在这个默克尔根里，
这个默克尔根是所有交易的摘要，
它指向区块中的所有交易。
这里是这个矿工的代码，
它只是挖掘了一个区块头，
我已经在网站上提供了这个代码，
我会在一会儿给你一个链接。
对于这个特定的矿工，
我知道成功的哈希是什么。
让我们把这个减少100。
如果我再次启动这个，
我已经增加了开始的nonce值，
所以再次强调，这是区块头。
这次，随机数不是从0开始，
而是从一个更高的数字开始。
如果我现在让它运行，
希望在大约100次之后，
当它找到一个低于目标值的区块哈希时，它会停止。
这里我们来看看，
如果你看到这个，
区块已经被挖出来了。
这个特定的区块哈希完全是随机的，
纯粹是运气使得区块哈希以这么多个零开头，
这个值低于目标值，
所以矿工们就是这样做的，
他们只是抓取一个区块头，
改变随机数，尽可能快地进行哈希。
这个理解起来有问题吗？
好的，
我会在最后添加这些链接，
你去网站learnmebitcoin.com看代码部分，
我已经把挖矿模拟器的代码放在这里了。
这是用Ruby写的，
我觉得这是一种简单易读的语言，
类似于Python。
我试图让这个尽可能简单，
所以如果你想开始哈希你自己的区块头，
你可以这样做。
你也可以在浏览器上，
打开learnmeabitcoin.com
你将能够看到这些最新的区块，
这些是区块头，
如果你点击序列化，
它会显示序列化的代码，
如果你对这个进行哈希，
它会产生这个区块头，
这是一个候选区块,
在尝试做同样的事情。
我很好奇，
这个是在你的机器上运行的吗？
这是实时的吗？
是的，这是实时的。
这是一个实时的候选区块，
这些都是实时的交易，
一切都在浏览器上。
好的，
这就是基础知识的介绍。
现在我将从技术角度来讲解，
基本上我要讲一遍同样的事情，
但是从程序员的角度来讲解。
如果你对编程和挖矿感兴趣，
这基本上就是和之前同样的内容，
只是从程序员的角度来看。
再次重复，
从内存池中获取交易，
填充你的区块，
然后你会得到一个候选区块，
然后你在顶部放置你的coinbase交易。
一个区块的第一笔交易总是coinbase交易，
这是矿工放在那里的。
这样你就可以领取区块奖励，
当前是比特币12.5个。
在选择了所有这些交易之后，
你会将coinbase交易放在区块的顶部的原因是什么？
每一笔交易都会有一个费用，
通过你的coinbase交易，
你可以收集所有这些费用。
所以，coinbase交易不仅仅是接收12.5个区块奖励，
你还可以根据这些费用的价值，
给自己发送13个或更多的比特币。
所以，
coinbase交易包括了费用是吗？
是的，
它不仅包括挖矿奖励。
你还有基础级别的区块奖励，
但是你可以根据每笔交易的费用，
给自己发送多少比特币。
so this means that miners will tend to
pick uh
uh
transactions with a higher exactly yes
uh so there we are we've got the
transfer one more question on that uh
yeah so i i remember seeing a graph
where uh
you know it showed me like uh
on the left the fees and on the right
like kind of how much time it will take
to mine that block yeah so uh
uh does this mean that
you know
if we put a very very low fee is it ever
possible that our transaction will never
get uh
never be part of a block is that ever
possible in your experience or what can
happen is so say you make a transaction
it'll go into the memory pool first um
if there's a lot of transactions in the
memory pool
um then you basically basically your
transaction is competing with all these
other transactions for space in a block
because a block
it's the way a block is
it used to be one megabytes worth of
transactions um it's roughly about 1.7
now
it uses a different metric called weight
but don't i'm not going to cover that
just now but um
what will happen is say you put such a
low fee on there
that um it doesn't make it into the
blocks are still hanging around in the
memory pool um
if your transaction stays in the memory
pool memory pool for longer than 72
hours
on average um
your
transaction will just get kicked out the
memory pool
so
you if you put a very low transaction a
fee on a transaction there's a chance
that it will never make it um one into a
into a candidate block or even it or
onto the blockchain right
so again in your experience what's like
the like the bare minimum let's say if i
want to send like five bucks to someone
you know or buy a coffee like three
bucks
uh what's what's the minimum
fee that i have to pay i mean
um i think wallets generally um
tend to
um
help you out with that but i don't think
they created it but
um
one way
what i would do is i would look at a cat
this candidate block and
transactions in general are ordered in a
candidate block from highest to lowest
fees not strictly but i would head
towards the bottom of this candidate
block and have a look at each of the fee
the fees on them and
um
uh
you can just basically add a fee that's
greater than the lowest fees yeah
exactly that's a
rough i mean that's like the simplest
way to do it in my opinion um
so
yeah yeah so again this is per byte i
think when you hovered over uh yeah so
fee per byte so this is uh
so the average
byte size of a transaction is that what
this is yeah so
um
so this this is a transaction
and um this
yeah this takes up um space in a block
so um then you set a fee on it but
you're basically paying for each
individual bytes so that the the bigger
the um
the transaction is in data wise uh the
more of a higher fee you want to put on
it to give you because
a miner but they will
select transactions um based on fee per
byte so basically which transactions are
giving them the most fee for the space
they're going to take up in the
candidate block
okay
um
so again just going to went through
mining again put your coinbase
transaction at the top
and then you can check the block header
same again you have a version number
um
this was like this null block and the
version of was one uh the way versions
numbers has cha the way version numbers
uh work now is different to how it used
to be they can be used for um voting um
i'm not going to cover that just now
it's going to run through um
simple block header then you have the
previous block name again just refer to
the block you're going to build on top
of build on top of which is basically
the tip of the blockchain
uh then you have the merkle root
so the way that works is um you have all
the transactions uh
in the block
i'm just moving these to the side just
for illustration purposes
and what you do you just run through
every single pair of transactions and
you hash them together
so remember the hash function and you
basically line these up
so one and two just line them up
together and hash them together and
they'll produce a
digest or hash result
and they do that for every single pair
of transactions
in the block
um if you end up with a transaction on
his own that doesn't have a pair all you
do is you just hash it with itself
and then that's the first round done you
have these four hashes from all these
pairs
then you just run through again
hash them all together hash each pair
together and you keep going on and
you'll end up with a single um
hash result
called the merkle root
now
the question is um
why
if you want to create a summary of all
the transactions in the block you're
hashing the transaction ids here
together by the way but um
if you want to create a summary or a
fingerprint for all the transactions in
the block why wouldn't you just hash
them all together like this in a more
simple way why would you do it in this
more elaborate
um tree structure
and the reason for that is
um say you you were given a merkle root
um
a merkel root and you want to check if
this transaction id
is present in this block
um the only way you could check it
would be to take
all of the other
transaction ids you need all the other
ones including the one you want to check
and then hash them together to get the
miracle root
um
to get the to get the hash sorry
but
with a miracle root um so you want to
check the presence of this hash here all
you actually need is you need this one
to create this one
and then if you've got that one and then
all you need is that one
and then you can create that one
and then only then is this one up here
and that will give you this miracle root
so the other one needed was it one two
three four five seven six um
transaction ids but this one only needed
uh three
so obviously it doesn't look like a
massive improvement but this is just a
simple block that if this is a lot
longer block with
thousands of transactions
then
you're needing a lot less transaction
ids to
check the presence of a single
transaction
i've not done this myself but
apparently this is useful and efficient
to um
do it this way so that's why we have
this tree structure for hashing because
it saves on checking for the presence of
transactions in our block yeah just one
question when you say that we we hash
like two transactions you're saying that
we just concatenate them and hash do a
chat yeah 256. exactly you just
concatenate the transaction ids
which are basically the hashes of the
time yeah so
you basically hash transaction data to
give you a transaction id and then you
yeah yeah
[Music]
um
so there we go um that's the merkel
route
uh time also in the block header
you have something called but you just
have the time which is a timestamp
um like so
but you don't the way the
time is encoded in the block header is
using unix time
which is the number of seconds since the
1st january 1970.
so this
blocks times timestamping so the human
representation is 12 may 2011 but in
unix time that would be this many
seconds
um
a quick note
on the time um these don't have to be
accurate
um they just have to be between a
certain minimum and maximum value
so um
the minimum value
you can set as the time for your block
header is the median time of the last 11
blocks
or basically the the time set that's
been the time of in the block header of
the sixth block down
so you can't have a time
uh any lower than that
that's the minimum bound
and then the maximum
um
the maximum
basically your node has its own time
uh when you run it it just uses your
computer's time and then when other
nodes connect to you they will send you
what their time is on their computer and
so your node will keep track of the
difference between
all of the times of the nodes you're
connected to
and if you put them in order and you
take the median time
of all the nodes you're connected to
um that's called the network average
time
so um
the maximum value of this time is the
network average time plus two hours
so can you repeat this
like quickly i mean i just got a little
confused so why is this time used and uh
is this the time to mine a block or
something i mean uh no uh no this is
this this time um i think this is i
think this is quite a bit unnecessary
necessary for me to explain um basically
the time is just you just stick the
current time of your computer um in the
block header but it's but it's not um
it doesn't have to be precise um
it's not yeah so basically it just has
to be between two certain values um as
long as it's a greater than um the time
of
the sixth block down
yeah or the meat of the median time of
the last 11 blocks
um it can't be any lower than that
because if you were to put a time lower
than that then it would get rejected by
the nodes you send it to and also the
maximum time is basically the current
time
plus two hours
but it's we used
um network average time is used which is
just the average time
of all the nodes that are connected to
you
um
so don't worry about that um but it's
basically all i'm saying is the time can
be
roughly an hour behind one or two hours
ahead
so it's not really if you see if a block
comes comes through and it has a time
like
before or ahead of like a different
block
it doesn't really matter it has this
sort of flexible sort of upper and lower
boundary
all right so that's the time um bits um
bits remember the target
bits is just a compact representation of
the target
so instead of putting the the current
target um
the entire target in the block header
what you what you do
is you just grab um the first three
significant bytes or the first six you
know significant characters after the
leading zeros and then you put that
there
and then
um you just grab the offset so how far
these
um three bytes are from the right
uh and that is there are 26 bytes from
the right here
or in hexadecimal 26 is 1a
so you just put that start there so bits
is just this compact representation of
the target
um
then that's it then then you just have
the nonce and you can set that to zero
and so this is all the basic data now um
for the block header
does that does it all these fields make
sense each part okay good um so now
we've got all the fields ready to be
mined
um we just have to get all the data into
the correct format
uh so this is just a bit of programming
just to make sure everything's in the
right order and format
each field um should be in hexa put it
all into hexadecimal
so
one is one in hexadecimal so this is
going to change but you just go through
every single field making sure that it's
all hexadecimal so
these two hexadecimal the time this is
in decimal at the moment so we just
convert that hex decimal and you do the
same for every other field
secondly
each field
must be a
fixed number of bytes
so there's only got one character in
here but the version field is four bytes
so if we convert that to four bytes it
looks like this
so one byte is two characters so zero
zero that's one byte and there are four
bytes in the version
um
then you just go through every single
field giving it
putting it into the correct um
size so this is already 32 bytes that's
already 32 bytes
the time's gonna be four bytes it's
already four bits same again four the
nonce then that's four bytes as well
so just for each field make sure that
you've padded it out padded it out
with the right number of bytes so this
basically means that when a computer can
read through each individual fields
easily
so that's all the
data in the right
format and the right field size
lastly the only
slightly frustrating thing with bitcoin
is that when you send
data to
um the nodes um
across the wire
you have to send the data in reverse
byte order which is called network byte
order
so um obviously we've got all this in
human readable human human readable byte
order but when you
hash and work with bitcoin data it has
to be in reverse byte order so you just
go through every single field and put it
into network byte order
which is just reversing each byte
so that's something that
well they tripped me up when i first
started mining i was like i was trying
to hash these block headers and i was
like why am i not getting the same
results it's because
you want to get everything in network
byte order
and just to show you i've made like a
little quick um
uh
script
so reverse bytes so if i put the
a b c d e
f one two three four
let me see
um the way that works is reverse byte
order you just split it all into each
individual byte so one byte is two
characters and then you just um reverse
the order of the bytes and that gives
you that so that's how it works so
you're not just reversing the string
you are um reversing each byte
so this might be a basic question but uh
one
so two characters is one byte yes yes
yeah
yep
um
that's just something i've learned
uh
i'm just looking at the c plus plus
uh i've not done c plus plus in a long
time
so character type size is one byte um
yeah no i i don't i don't know that much
deep about computer science um but all i
know is yeah
i'm doing this more like a top down sort
of level i i've just learned that um two
characters translates as one byte so
yeah
um so there we are now we've got all the
data finally in the right order um all
you do then you just concatenate each
individual field together like that so
this is the block header
now it's ready to put inside to put into
the hash function
um as i mentioned um sha-256 simple
hashing algorithm 256
is used
um but in bitcoin everything gets hashed
twice
um
it's just the way it was designed i
don't think it provides any massive
benefits it's just the way that
bitcoin hashes things
um
so you just put this into hash function
spits our result and then spits out then
you hash the result to get you another
result and that's the
final hash
um quick note um
when when you hash things in bitcoin um
this is in hexadecimal but you convert
it into binary first so you put binary
data into the hashing function
and then
that'll spit out a binding result then
you put the binary result into the
second
hashing function
that'll spit out a second binary digest
and then when you convert that
second digest
back into hexadecimal
that'll give you the
um
block hash but obviously this is in
reverse
uh network byte order again so if you
reverse it
then that's in the more human
uh format so if you compare this
to the target you want to make sure it's
in you want to reverse it back into
uh
non-network byte order
so
so there we go um so this i've only
covered these things because they just
trip you up i mean get in the fields
it's quite simple but then get anything
into the right order then converting it
to binary and then switching it back
again
um that's what'll trip you up if you're
trying to minor block header or hash a
block header for yourself
all right so this was the block header
on the left which already had the fields
in reverse network order right
uh yes yes
okay then you
uh
do a double hash of that yeah and you
convert it to hex and
you converted that again in reverse
i reversed it i reversed it back
okay
um yeah and this is how this is
like if you mind the block this is the
hash that you would send on to the
network is that uh
um let's say that you end up mining a
block and let's say you get a nuance
that is like below a target value yeah
uh
what do you do next yeah i mean okay i
think i should cover that now i think um
so okay um
you don't actually send the block hash
um you just send basically the block
header and the transactions
so
okay but i'm just i don't think you have
to if you're programming you wouldn't
you might not have to reverse it this is
just so i can
display the results correctly uh in a
sort of a human way
so again so now like a minor you just
change the nonce now i'm incrementing it
from
um zero one two three four five and so
on so there you are obviously this is in
network byte order
and so on eventually you'll get a
uh
hash uh this below the target if you're
lucky
then that's mind so when you mind the
actual block
so this is done now so this is a
successful block header
so
if you send this block header to anyone
else they can hash it for themselves and
they get the same result
that's what i think that's what they
call proof of work because you can just
send this block header to anyone and
they can prove for themselves that the
hash is below the target so what you
what you do then is you send this block
uh to all the nodes you're connected to
and what you're actually sending them is
all of the transaction data concatenated
together for each transaction
um
before that you put like a little
transaction counter
which is just a byte
it's a it's a very very variable sized
byte i haven't covered it but it's on
the website um
just tells you how many transactions are
in the block and then before that you
have the block header so this is what
gets sent to
um all the nodes so you don't have to
send the
block hash because they can calculate it
for themselves
so um
that's how mining works um what i
thought i would do now is um try and
show you how you could uh
mine a actual live block
so yeah
right so um if you run a bitcoin node
um you have the um bitcoin cli um
command which allows you to ask the
bitcoin no questions and one of them you
can ask them is to get block template
so what that will do that will take your
current memory pool and
gather the highest value transactions
that would fill up a
block
and
give them to you so this is showing me
all of the transactions that would make
a
candidate block
so um let me just move this down sorry
um
so
uh if we to if i just quickly examine um
the information
inside here if you if you um use bitcoin
cli help get block template that will
show you um all the fields that will
give you all the fields they'll produce
um but if i just quickly
um
what we want to see basically to minor
block is to create a block header from
all these transactions
so bitcoin cli get block template
and i'm going to use um
grep just to search for the fields that
we want
i'm using rg which is a variant of grep
and so we want to find we want to have a
version
number
we want the previous block
then we want the merkle root
um
then we want
time
then bits
then there's a nonce but
we're going to provide our own nuns so
we don't need that
so looking at the
i spelt that wrong
there we are so
looking at the results of block get
block template it's given us the version
the previous block hash it's also giving
us the time current time and bits
so it's changing the current time
so what it's not giving us is a miracle
root
um
for some i don't know why it's not um
but what you can do
um what it is giving you is um
this is just a
json parser
it has given you um
a list of
transactions
and it has given you all the transaction
ids so if we just go through each one
and say give us
the transaction ids
now let's need to put that in quotes
there we are so these are all the
transaction ids
in this candidate block
so now we've got all those transaction
ids we just need to create our own
merkle route for them
so
um luckily i've written my own script
and that will take in a list of
transactions and create a miracle route
from them
um i've made this available on the
website i'll show it in the moment
so if i just do that
then we have a miracle root
so now um we've got all the data we need
to mine a
both or basically to construct a block
header
so if you just bare with me for five
minutes i'm gonna go through each field
and um
yeah so first of all uh we need to get
the version
oh that's done wrong
okay
so there we are using get a get block
template this is the current version uh
like i said they've changed a bit so um
this is
they've been used to vote for voting so
this is why it's a very high number but
i'm not going to spend it now just take
it as it is
um
so this is the version number but
obviously it's in uh decimal so to
convert that into
hexadecimal first first so there we are
and then
now it's in hexadecimal this is already
um four bytes
so i just swap the byte order or swap
the endianness because sometimes
um
the byte order is referred to referred
to as endianness
um
so there we are so this is the
uh
version all set up and ready to go so
i'll just
trim the end off that
because i'm going to concatenate it all
together so if i save this as a
variable
there we have so just
echo that out to check
so that's the version done so next up
after the version is the
version previous block
so previous block
hash
so this is the block hash for the
previous block
let me just trim off the
uh quotes
and then
uh it's already in hex decimal it's
already 32 bytes so what i need to do is
sort the byte order or put it into
little endian
so there we are and then i can save this
then
as the previous block variable
next up then is the miracle root
uh
obviously we don't get a miracle root
um from the get block template um
command but what does give us is the
list of transactions
and for each of those it will give us um
a transaction id
oops
oh well i just lost that
oh there it is
so there we go
and from these i can get the merkle root
there we are and then it's already in
hexadecimal it's already in
32 bytes i just need to sort the byte
order
again
uh there we are i'll save that as a
variable
i'm going to call
nearly there i know it's a bit laborious
but uh so that's yeah so version
previous block miracle root uh then we
have the time
um for some reason
um
even though the get plot template
doesn't give you the merkel route it
does give you
the current time on your computer
um
actually it gives you a
valid time i'm not sure if this is um
i don't know but this is definitely a
valid time but what you could do if you
want to use that if you want to use the
get blocked
template time you can use the date
function from a programming language
so if you just this gives you the number
of seconds
in unix times if i just use that
um just need to get it into hexadecimal
like so
one two three four five six seven so 24
bytes
uh
then we
it to and
uh reverse bite order
there we are so there is that's the time
ready
enough
and
that's the time done
lastly uh bits
which is the compact version of the
target
there it is you just trim off the
uh
quotes
and then put into reverse byte order
and there it is so now we've got all the
basic block header data
uh
ready
in the right format so if i
just construct the block header from
each individ each of those individual
fields
that is the version
the previous block
the miracle root
then
time
and then bits
so check what that looks like
there it is there's our block header and
so all we have all we haven't put there
now is the nonce
so
if we wanted to
mine this we just need to create a loop
that will
keep hashing this
uh
block header and we'll adjust the nonce
increment it with every attempt
so the nonce um will look like we'll
start off with zero
um but obviously we need to get this in
the right format um so we need to
convert that to um
uh extradition
sorry thank you
uh then at least so like so
uh but obviously this needs to be um
four bytes in length so i made a little
function that will just make sure it's
the right size
and then convert the swap end in
obviously it's not very interesting
because i've used the number zero but if
i wish to use like a much higher nonce
value
uh like that
then like so it's prepared it for me
so i'm not going to append this to it
yet what i'm going to do i'm going to
create a loop so while true
do
you want to
oh wait there before that i want to set
a variable to
an increment incremented variable ready
so while true
uh
do
want to
create the nonce
which is going to be like i just showed
you um
echo
i
uh they want to get it in deck
hex decimal
four byte field size swap endian
uh
trim off the end
uh so that's the non stun
then our attempt at
trying to mine the block will be just
the
uh block header we created
plus the nonce at the end
and then what we want to do is we want
to hash that
um all together so i've made a little
function that will hash for me um
called hash 256 because this
is just the the double hash converts the
binary then double hashes it i'm going
to hash 256 um the attempt
and
every after every attempt we want to
uh increment the nonce so let
uh i must plus so just increment the
notes from
this
number here actually
uh and then done so hopefully this will
work there we are so now
this is hashing
um
very slowly uh a block header the
current block header obviously it's very
slow it took me a long time but this is
actually mine trying to mine a block
um
so if that was
lucky
what you'd probably do you'd have some
code in there that would stop
um when you if yeah if it reaches the
target target yeah and then what you do
then there's a function and bitcoin cli
called um submit block
and you would just submit
the header the transaction count
and all the transaction data so if you
constructed a successful block header
you would send that to all the nodes
you're connected to and you'd use that
do that using the
submit block um
bitcoin cli command
is there a way to uh get the target
value from the bitcoin cli
uh yeah so um i think it's included in
um bitcoin cli get block template
yeah so um i think it's it's
extending the block
yeah so there it is so this is the
current target so you could grab that
target and then stick that summer into
yeah into the for loop
yeah but obviously um
that that hashing there was very very
slow
oh yeah yeah i i totally get it yeah you
probably want to do that yeah
in a single programming language this is
just on bash just for quick sort of
illustration purposes but that just goes
to show like how basically how simple uh
mining is really the hardest part is
just getting the data in the right order
um but after that it's just you just
increment a nonsense hash it and
hopefully you get a result a lucky
result
um
i think yeah so that's everything i
wanted to explain about how mining works
um
that's all the technical stuff but
obviously is
probably a lot simpler than it's made
out to be
um
on the website i've made all this code
available so each those little um hex
decimal converters and decimal
converters
and the swap endianness they're all here
there's a miracle root function on here
written in php
um it's not the prettiest um but it will
take a
list of
transaction ids and create american
route for you
i might not want to use it in production
you might want to use a different
library i'm sure there's loads of
bitcoin libraries out there with their
own merkle root um functions for you to
use
um
is there any questions about
that sort of mining process no i mean
this this was really awesome great
thanks a lot
uh
just curious any any experience with
those heavy duty miners
no i've not actually mined myself
because like we said like it's so
inefficient to mine on your laptop if
you wanted to mine now it's not a hobby
thing you have to sort of
you know buy a professional mining rig
and run it like a proper business which
is a shame because that takes mining out
of the hands of the average person then
so
um
yeah so i think if you want to get into
mind you you would have to really commit
to it
it's not just right gone yeah right
right even those guys would be doing
like at a fundamental level they would
be doing the same thing right just
faster
yes so they're just doing the exact same
thing constructing block header and just
hashing it as fast as you can like this
whole construction of the block header
is simple and takes a
absolute fraction of a second to do and
then the whole mining then the whole
meat of mining is hashing as fast as
possible
um
[Music]
i think i've
don't think i've missed anything i think
i've covered everything i wanted to
sorry i know that's a bit repetitive in
parts uh no no no this was a great
explanation again yeah thanks a lot for
this yeah
but i think if you're starting out with
bitcoin um
one of the best ways to learn i think is
to try and
mine your own block header i think it's
quite simple to do and i think mining is
one of the sort of first fundamental
parts of how bitcoin works so if you can
figure out how to mine a block header
or hash a block header that's a great
stepping stone i'll give you the tools
then to figure out about the all the um
hexadecimal and network byte order and
how to hash and then you can take those
tools then and use them in other parts
of bitcoin like in you know with
transactions and all that
so this would be my first place to start
if you were to try coding with
bitcoin
i mean you you're obviously probably not
going to
set up your minor but as a sort of
learning experience this is a great
place to start
so yeah if you want to browse block
headers just go into livia bitcoin this
is the blockchain
and you can browse to each individual
block and see all the different block
headers and test for yourself
then you can get the same
block cache results
nice
yep
so uh thank you very much for that uh
that was good to do
thanks
no worries so yeah